Ghulam Sarwar



ghulamsarwar244@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/ghulam-sarwar

♦ +1 902 809 7861

SUMMARY

Highly curious, results driven, and strategic business intelligence and analytics professional with more than 10 years of experience in business analysis, data management, and enterprise business intelligence & analytics to guide and enable business transformation and decision-making.

Strengths include:

- **■** 10+ years of experience, and master's degree in engineering, and advanced diploma in business intelligence & analytics.
- ► Certified & trained in CRM, stakeholder management and communication, business and technical analysis, risk and impact analysis, business strategy, IT strategy, enterprise architecture, enterprise data management, Microsoft SQL Server, Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC), Leadership and Teamwork.
- ► Certified & trained in lean six sigma, statistics, operational excellence, decision making, and business process re-engineering.
- **☞** Expert in managing, designing, developing, and deploying Data Models, Databases, ETL Projects, Cubes, Reports, Dashboards and Data Catalogs.
- Expert in Microsoft, Oracle, IBM Cognos, and Google analytics platforms.
- ► Proven proficiency of BI Tools: SQL SERVER, SSMS, SSIS, SSAS, SSRS, Visual Studio, MS Visio, SharePoint Performance Point, Excel Power BI, Power BI, Tableau, IBM Cognos, Oracle BI tools, SAP BW, and Informatica.
- ► Proven proficiency of programming languages: SQL, T-SQL, PL/SQL, DAX, MDX, Python, R, and C++.
- ► Proven advanced skills of business intelligence projects planning, business requirements definition, designing, development, and deployment of technology architecture, dimensional data models, ETL packages, data warehouse, cubes, dashboards, and analytical BI applications.
- ► Proven skills of problem analysis, service design and implementation, change management, release management, and risk & impact assessment.
- ► Proven knowledge of frameworks: TOGAF, ITIL, Zachman, COBIT, Agile based BI Projects Delivery, Scrum, DevOps, IIBA® Global Business Analysis Core Standard, and PMBOK.
- **►** Hold Canadian citizenship and full reliability security clearance.
- ► Proficient in more than 7 languages: English, Hindi, Urdu, Punjabi, Arabic, Persian, French.

EXPERIENCE



Senior Business Intelligence Developer

Emera Energy

Jan 2022 - Present (2 months +)

- **☞** Manage, analyze, design, develop and implement ETL packages, reports, and BI architecture.
- Elicit and manage requirements of stakeholders, business processes, BI solutions, and technology.
- Optimize and recommend better BI solutions.

Community Volunteer - IT Business Analyst Professional Mentor

Immigrant Services Association of Nova Scotia

Nov 2013 - Present (8 years 4 months +)

- From Offer mentoring to young graduates and youths to improve their professional skills in the domains of business process improvement, IT, Engineering and Analytics.
- © Coordinate community events and support integration of immigrants.
- ☞ Support tax filing community events.



Senior Business Intelligence and Analytics Professional - IT Business Analyst

Medavie Blue Cross / Croix Bleue Medavie

Sep 2020 - Dec 2021 (1 year 4 months)

- **☞** Elicited, communicated, and managed business requirements, functional & non-functional requirements of business intelligence & analytics solutions, and specifications of technology architecture.
- Planned, developed, and deployed changes requests, enhancements, and projects of business intelligence and analytics solutions.
- Pesigned, developed, and maintained regular releases, job schedules, EDW, ETL, Cubes, Reports, and Dashboards.



Business Intelligence Specialist – IT Business Analyst

Medavie Blue Cross / Croix Bleue Medavie

Apr 2019 - Sep 2020 (1 year 6 months)

- ► Analyzed the requirements of each business process, its users, and existing information systems, and created the matched data solutions.
- reports, and dashboards. reports, and dashboards. reports, and dashboards. tested, and distributed the interactive dashboards and visuals across demographic, temporal, and geographic dimensions.
- **☞** Leveraged the power of descriptive, diagnostic, predictive and prescriptive analytics capabilities to recommend better IT and business solutions.
- **☞** Debugged and tested ETL schedules and jobs.
- **☞** Built and implemented projects of data integration, data analysis and reporting based on the principles of dimensional data modeling, and the requirements of business stakeholders & business processes.
- Created BI applications and data fix related change requests, risk assessments, business impact analysis, release package builds and release deployment plans.
- **☞** Employed techniques of Unix scripting, power shell scripting, and continuous integration & delivery to manifest automation.
- **☞** Leveraged tools such as MS SQL Server, MS Visual Studio, SSIS/SSAS/SSRS, Oracle Database System, OWB, Power BI, and MS Office Suit to produce BI solutions.



Business Intelligence and analytics Trainee - IT Business Analyst Training

Nova Scotia Community College

Jan 2018 - Apr 2019 (1 year 4 months)

- **☞** Database Design and Implementation
- **☞** Data Reporting
- **☞** Data Provisioning with ETL
- **☞** Business Analysis
- Introduction to Statistical Learning
- **☞** Applied Data Analytics

- **☞** Introduction to Business Intelligence
- **☞** Ethics and Law in Data Analytics



■ Team Leader – Business Analyst

Park indigo Canada

Sep 2014 - Apr 2019 (4 years 8 months)

- F Monitored, troubleshot, and operated the Parking Information System, Databases, Transaction Systems, and Payment Systems.
- Erabled improvement and automation in the parking transaction process by incorporating better digital parking solutions.
- F Collaborated, coordinated, and managed the parking team to work efficiently and effectively. F Maintained and prepared the daily revenue reports, shift reports, cash inventory reports, inspection checklists.
- Earned the values of responsibility, accountability, and integrity.



EIT Trainee – Business Analyst Trainee

Immigrant Services Association of Nova Scotia

Apr 2015 - Nov 2015 (8 months)

- Figure 1 Improved the communication skills, project management skills, and cultural competency skills.
- © Completed assignments, projects, and presentations.
- Enhanced collaboration skills.



■ Vice-Principal – Business Analyst

Red-C Institute of Engineering and Technology, Islamabad, Pakistan

Sep 2010 - Sep 2013 (3 years 1 month)

- Fr Analyzed the business vision-goal-strategy, proposed, and implemented the best IT solutions to enhance student's learning experience.
- □ Designed the curriculum, instructed, and assessed the performance of more than 300 technology students.
- Fresented the critical insights on the graduation rates of students, investigated the reasons of student's dropouts, and recommended the critical necessary actions to improve the institutional performance.
- Delivered the lectures on the data analysis & reporting of oil and gas reservoirs, drilling operations, welllogging & well testing, project management, applied linear algebra, and applied calculus.
- Achieved the best teaching award and promoted to vice-principal role.



🚆 Internee – Business Analyst

Dewan Petroleum (Pvt.) Limited

Jun 2010 - Sep 2010 (4 months)

- used the Excel Power BI and commercial software, produced the critical insights on the data of the reservoir, production, well logging and drilling operations.
- F Documented and prepared the reports and recommended the critical & necessary actions for IOR.
- © Conducted the field visits and analyzed the drilling and production operations.

EDUCATION



Dalhousie University

Master's degree, Engineering 2013 - 2015



Nova Scotia Community College

Advance Diploma, Business Intelligence Analytics

2018 - 2019

COURSES: Data Provisioning With ETL, Business Analysis, Database Design-II, Applied Statistics,

Database Management and Administration, Data Analytics, Business Intelligence, Data Warehouse,

Ethics and Laws in Data Analytics, Capstone Project



Winiversity of Engineering and Technology, Lahore

Bachelor's degree, Engineering

2006 - 2010

COURSES: C++, Advanced Calculus, Applied Statistics, Well Logging & Well Testing Data Analysis & Reporting, Reservoir & Production data Analysis & Reporting, Applied Simulation

LICENSES & CERTIFICATIONS



CSX Cyber-security Fundamentals Certification - ISACA.org

SKILLS

Business Strategy, Performance Management, KPIs, Dashboard, Reports, Data Analysis, Data Warehousing, Data Integration, Dimensional Data Modelling • Teaching and training, Effective communication & presentation, Project Management & control, SQL, Python, R and C#. • Data-driven Decision Making, Business Process Re-engineering, Analytical Applications, Data Management, Data Privacy & Information Security • Extract, Transform, Load (ETL) • Microsoft Power BI • PL/SQL • Microsoft SQL Server • Oracle SQL Developer • Transact-SQL (T-SQL) • SQL

HONORS & AWARDS



Honors & Awards

- F Achieved 13 excellent academic & work performance awards, 2 swimming & cricket sports awards, 5best teaching awards, and 2 volunteering awards.
- Served as a vice-president of Gojra Group of Engineers and has helped more than 200 needy &deserving students.